so bante I feel that my practice has
become dry and mechanical how can I
cultivate joy and inspiration without
relying on worldly
pleasures pronunciation seems a bit
boring well I think probably the
quickest way
to regain your inspiration is to um
reintroduce the sense of urgency
so if things are getting stale and
boring is because you're not basically
recognizing the urgency of the
practice because you've been you're
taking things for granted you're you you
you fell off the right context they
would maintain the perception of
maintain the perception of
danger um
change nonability a lot closer to you to
your day-to-day lives so um if you're if
you're not feeling that is because you
haven't been frequently pondering on it
and reflecting it and you've been
neglecting it
basically and started just falling into
mechanical ways of practice and then
when you stop and think about it it just
feels like well you know kind of
optional so you need to basically set
time aside during the day and bring up
[Music] the most likely unpleasant scenarios
the most likely unpleasant scenarios
that they would reintroduce the a sense
of urgency such as getting
sick losing things that are deare to
you what could go wrong possibility of
yeah things going wrong dying just
because those things remain
unchanged they're equally
present whether you think about them or
not um it's just the people choose to
not think about them I also think that
if a person is sort of uh uninspired
got no energy for practice I think that
it probably stems from needing an
upgrade in Restraint actually like they
can upgrade their precepts and then
things start getting a bit more for sure
yeah yeah well then probably serious
yeah yeah then probably you wouldn't
even need
[Music] to think and reflect that much because
to think and reflect that much because
um the pressure of the restraint will
amplify everything MH and then things
will become a lot more sharper
a lot more acutely
felt so there's no way you would feel
stale yeah like there must be something
what are you using for distraction yeah
but presumably person is asking that
question to us so he knows where the
emphasis is so presumably he's keeping
the precepts um that's not an issue and then
precepts um that's not an issue and then
he's still reaching the point of just
things feel stale
and mechanical then it's because yeah
you stop thinking about the right themes
precepts in and of themselves will
not but yes as you say practically
speaking goes hand in hand with lack of
restraint like you you stop thinking
about the right things because you've
been thinking about the wrong things
yeah because you've been not restraining
the wrong
themes the wrong perceptions and so on
maybe if it's not against the precepts
that's like you might feel it's fine but
fundamentally it's still like
um Within the the um along the
principles of of sensuality and ill will
and so on so yes you don't go as far as
to break the precepts but you are
indulging such thoughts actions that
within the precepts getting used to it
comfortable within it and then you stop
thinking about the the actual work that
still hasn't been done and the safety
that still hasn't been achieved and in
that way it's like you you cutting
yourself off from the the joy that can
be achieved through that well through a
complete overcoming of sensuality of
course Jo J but uh yeah like that it's a
bit of a dry Zone yeah yeah exactly yeah
you have to walk through through a bit
of a dry Zone yeah